John L. Cutler Research Collection Relating to Gilbert Patten
John L. Cutler Research Collection Relating to Gilbert Patten
1925-2002
1925-1938
Cutler, John L.
0.5 linear ft.
Research notes for a book about dime novel author Gilbert Patten, aka Burt L. Standish. Collection includes notes, photographs, printed material, essays, correspondence.
2740154
Biographical History
Gilbert Patten (pen name of Burt L. Standish) was the author of a pulp series for Street & Smith called The Amazing Frank Merriwell Stories. John L. Cutler was the author of Gilbert Patten and his Frank Merriwell saga: a study in sub-literary fiction, 1896-1913 (1934). Ryan K. Anderson is the author of Frank Merriwell and the Fiction of All-American Boyhood (2015). This collection of Cutler's research material was given to Anderson by Cutler's daughter Carolyn, and subsequently donated by Anderson.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John L. Cutler Research Collection Relating to Gilbert Patten consists of research material for Cutler's book Gilbert Patten and his Frank Merriwell saga: a study in sub-literary fiction, 1896-1913. includes correspondence, Patten memorabilia, and research material.
Correspondence contains Cutler's correspondence with Patten himself, as well as with dime novel collector Charles Bragin and others. There is also one letter from Cutler's daughter Carolyn to Ryan K. Anderson.
Patten memorabilia contains two photographs of Patten along with covers and full issues of several of Patten's stories, written under the name Burt Standish.
Research material contains material accumulatd by Cutler relating to Patten and to dime novels in general, including articles by and about Patten, a questionnaire compiled by Cutler and completed by Patten, a dime novel bibliography, and assorted other items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by name or type of material.
Related Material
is also the repository for the
records of dime novel and pulp publisher Street & Smith
. In addition, we have a large number of dime novels and pulp magazines cataloged in our Rare Books holdings; please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Bragin, Charles.; Ellis, Milton, 1885-1947.; Standish, Burt L., 1866-1945.; Standish, Burt L., 1866-1945. -- Famous Frank Merriwell stories.; Street & Smith.; Tip top weekly.; Dime novels -- History and criticism.; Bibliographies.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Genealogies (histories); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Research notes.; Authors.; Biographers.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ryan K. Anderson, 2004.
Inventory
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Cutler, Carolyn (Cutler's daughter), 2002; to donor Ryan Anderson, about her father (Box 1)
  - Cutler, John, with Charles Bragin (dime novel collector), 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Cutler, John, with Milton Ellis (professor, University of Maine), 1932; 1934 (Box 1)
  - Cutler, John, with Alice Gardner Morris (Patten's ex-wife), 1935 (Box 1)
  - Cutler, John, with Gilbert Patten, 1931-1934; undated (Box 1)
  - Cutler, John, with Street & Smith, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Cutler, John, miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Patten memorabilia
  - Beadle's New York Dime Library No. 71, cover (Box 1)
  - Jesse James Stories No. 1, full issue (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Patten (Box 1)
  - Tip Top Weekly #256, cover (Box 1)
  - Tip Top Weekly #256, full issue (Box 1)
- Research material
  - Articles about Patten, 1925; 1932,; 1934,; 1938 (Oversize 1)
  - Articles by Patten, 1931-1932; 1934,; 1937; includes "Dime novel days: My start as a writer" from Saturday Evening Post (Oversize 1)
  - Dime Novel Bibliography, Charles Bragin, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Essay on Munsey Publishing House, author not given, undated (Box 1)
  - Maine 1850 census notes (Box 1)
  - Notes on dime novels, index cards (Box 1)
  - Patten genealogical information, family trees on loose sheets, small notebook with notes on Patten family (Box 1)
  - Questionnaires, completed by Patten (Box 1)